Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
Most of us want to live longer.
And if we could locate
that fountain of youth,
we would probably
take a sip or two.
However, there is a hormone
already in our body
that does something very similar.
It’s a longevity hormone
called FGF21.
Here’s our first story.
In the year 2000, a new human
hormone was discovered.
It was the 21st documented
fibroblast growth factor;
so, they called it FGF21.
Since its discovery, FGF21 has
emerged as a key agent for
promotion of metabolic and artery
health, leanness, and longevity.
Inject it into fat monkeys,
and they lose body weight
without reducing food intake,
and not just a little—
a 27 percent drop in body fat
eating the same amount.
In mice, it increases their
lifespan 30 to 40 percent,
comparable to lifelong caloric
restriction, but again
was achieved without
decreasing food intake.
The researchers conclude that
FGF21 could potentially be
used as a hormone therapy to
extend lifespan in mammals,
which has gotten big pharma
salivating, raising the question
“Can aging be ‘drugged’?”
And that’s not all it can do.
The idea that one drug
can treat obesity, diabetes,
dyslipidemia (like high
cholesterol), and hypertension
all at once might have
seemed impossible a few years ago
but is now a tantalizing
and exciting prospect.
The reason you can’t just give
people straight FGF21 is that
it gets rapidly broken down in the body;
so, you’d have to get injections like
every hour or two around the clock.
So, drug companies are
trying to patent a variety of
longer-acting FGF21 look-alikes.
And indeed, give people
a little PF-05231023
and they can lose about
10 pounds in 25 days,
along with dramatic drops in
triglycerides and cholesterol.
But then, the side effects
of these new-fangled drugs
started cropping up.
Okay, so what about this:
we package the FGF21 gene into
a virus and then inject the virus
and have it stitch extra
FGF21 genes into our DNA.
Or you can just lace
on your running shoes.
Exercise boosts FGF21 levels,
which may in fact
be one of the reasons
exercise is so good for us.
Which works better, though,
aerobic exercise—eight weeks
of running training—or resistance
exercise—eight weeks of weights?
The answer is both, but the
resistance exercise edged out
the running, a 42 percent
increase in FGF21 versus
a 25 percent increase in
the aerobic exercise group.
Okay, but what can we do with food?
Yeah, you could try
engineering and injecting it,
but wouldn’t it be easier to
just stimulate our own endogenous,
natural production through diet?
One way is through no diet at all.
You may have noticed it’s been
dubbed the starvation hormone.
That’s because fasting induces
FGF21, but not just a day or two.
Physiologically, FGF21
expression is markedly increased
in response to fasting/starvation.
But, unlike mice, which
show an increase after
just six hours of fasting,
humans don’t get a notable surge
in FGF21 until after a week.
Fasting can quadruple FGF21,
but it takes 10 days of fasting,
which is the very poster child of
an unsustainable eating pattern.
So, how do you get the benefits
without the starvation?
Might a ketogenic diet
be able to mimic the fast?
Nope. Keto diets don’t work.
In fact, keep it up for a few months,
and you can actually get a
significant decline in levels.
High-fat diets may
even interfere
with the boost you
get from exercise.
What kind of diet
does work, then?
We'll find out next.
Over a century ago, fasting
was hailed not only as
a means of combating
“cerebral lassitude,”
but also for the prolongation
of healthy longevity.
If that turns out to be true,
FGF21 might be a missing link.
FGF21 is characterized as a
systemic enhancer of longevity.
It can be boosted
through prolonged fasting,
but thankfully there are
other, less drastic measures,
such as more carbs or less protein.
Give people lots of starchy foods,
and you can shoot up FGF21 levels.
The healthiest sources would
likely be whole grains and beans,
since butyrate appears
to boost FGF21, too,
and we get that from fiber.
That’s one of the
things our good gut bugs
make from fiber-rich foods.
Circulating FGF21 levels are
also increased dramatically
when you eat a lower protein diet.
Over 150% increase within four weeks.
And when I say protein
restriction, it can just be
restricting protein intake
down from the typical excess
that most Americans get down
to the recommended amount.
The recommended daily allowance
of protein for most men
is 56 grams of protein a day,
though most American men
are getting over 100.
So, if you take men getting the
typical excess of about 112 grams
a day and reduce them
down to 64, which again
is still more than the
recommended 56—so the protein
“restricted” group was still
getting more than enough protein—
you can essentially double
FGF21 levels in the blood.
That may help explain
why despite them getting
significantly more calories,
they lost more body fat.
How can you eat 300 more
calories a day and still lose
two more pounds of straight body fat?
By just bringing your protein
levels down to normal levels.
Who hasn’t fantasized about
a diet that allows
ingestion of excess calories
that are burned off effortlessly
by ramping up fat burning?
So, maybe we should play down protein
to play up metabolism, thanks to FGF21.
Even just a quite modest protein
restriction regimen down
to recommended levels may have
significant clinical benefits.
Now, this was after a month and a half.
A similar study found that
even less protein restriction,
taking men down to just 73 grams a day,
resulted in a six-fold increase
in FGF21 within a single week,
accompanied by a significant
increase in insulin sensitivity.
They conclude that “dietary protein dilution”
promotes metabolic health in humans.
Evidence suggesting that a
lower protein intake is positively
associated with increased health, survival,
and insulin sensitivity
has continued to mount,
but we weren’t sure exactly how,
but maybe FGF21 provides an explanation.
Interestingly, the studies were
feeding people nine percent
of calories from protein, which
is about what the Okinawans
were getting when they
were one of the healthiest,
longest-living populations in the world.
You may remember my videos
on methionine restriction
to both fight cancer and
as a life-extension strategy.
Methionine is an amino
acid found predominantly
in animal proteins, and
so one could achieve
methionine restriction by
cutting down on animal foods.
That may actually be an FGF21 effect.
Methionine restriction
boosts levels so much so,
it’s been called the
most important mediator
of the metabolic reprogramming
in methionine restriction.
So, some proteins may be more
important to restrict than others.
The highest methionine levels are in meat.
Legumes (which are beans,
split peas, chickpeas, and lentils)
have about three times
less methionine than meat.
FGF21 has been proposed as
a potential mediator of the
protection from cancer,
autoimmune diseases, obesity,
and diabetes afforded by
strictly plant-based diets.
Maybe that’s one of the reasons
whole food plant-based diets
have been shown to have
such extraordinary results.
Take Dr. Esselstyn’s work,
for example, showing that
the number one killer of men
and women can be largely halted
or reversed, and risk of
heart attack almost eliminated,
with the help of a whole
food, low-fat vegan diet.
This benefit cannot be attributed
solely to cholesterol reduction,
as we have these new powerful
cholesterol-lowering drugs
now that can force
cholesterol levels as low as
healthy eaters but appear
to have less effect.
So, the marked benefits reported
by Esselstyn evidently reflect
a variety of protective mechanisms
associated with whole food
plant-based diets, and FGF21
may be one of those mechanisms.
So, it’s not just the fat and
cholesterol, but the quantity
and quality of protein
may also be playing a role.
But there’s never been a
study to see whether vegans
do indeed have higher
levels of FGF21…until now.
I’m glad I didn’t just pass on
this study based on the title.
In addition to studying
New Zealand obese mice,
they investigated the
circulating FGF21 levels
among those eating plant-based,
and then put it to the
test by removing meat
from other people’s diets
to see if FGF21 would go up.
And…FGF21 levels were
markedly higher in vegan humans
compared with omnivores,
and they went up when
the omnivores were switched
to vegetarian diets after just four days.
And not just a little. FGF21
levels increased by 232 percent
before and after just
four days free of meat.
The bottom line is that “the
various fasting approaches
are likely to have limited
efficacy, particularly on aging
and conditions other than
obesity, unless combined
with high-nourishment diets such
as the moderate calorie intake
and mostly plant-based Mediterranean
or Okinawa "low-protein" diets,
by which they mean the
recommended amount of protein.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.